In this section, let's take a look at how we, as AI product managers,
how do we track the effectiveness of the algorithm
In fact, the steps for an AI product manager to follow algorithm requirements
varies depending on different business scenarios
and the company's organizational structure varies
There can indeed be some differences.
For example, if your company has its own algorithm
middle-office algorithm
The platform already has many algorithmic capabilities.
So the new algorithmic requirements you propose
You should first check if the existing capabilities of the mid-platform can meet the requirements.
If it cannot be met
then you proceed to make the construction requirements
If you currently proceed with this algorithm
This scenario is extremely complex
possibly during the evaluation phase of this requirement
already requires the involvement of algorithm engineers
jointly evaluate the complexity of this algorithm
After we break down this scenario
some sub-requirements may need to be proposed
For each such algorithm,
We need to clarify the inputs and outputs in this context.
So here I will give you three general steps
If you need to develop a new algorithm requirement
You can match these general steps.
Make flexible adjustments according to different situations.
Step 1: Propose the algorithm requirements
As an AI product manager
If you are already clear about the requirements of this algorithm
what needs to be done
then you can clarify this requirement
What is the input and output range of it
Then we need to provide it to the R&D engineers
and to clarify the current algorithm requirement
What are the business metrics that should be achieved?
what value should this metric reach
can meet our launch requirements
The second point
continuously monitor the performance
You need to continuously communicate with the algorithm in an iterative manner
Understand its implementation approach
and provide some annotated data required for algorithm training
and continuously track the experimental results
Finally, conduct a multi-dimensional data validation.
After everything is OK, we will proceed with the launch.
Third, continuously optimize the performance
After the algorithm requirements are met
The product manager needs to continuously collect some bad cases
to collaborate with the algorithm team to train the model
to improve our business metrics
Let me give you an example
A certain company was reviewing the user conversation records when
it is often found that when users are in a negative emotional state
The robot's response remains a matter-of-fact reply.
This makes the overall conversation feel quite stiff and unnatural.
For example, in the following scenario
The parrot said it's killing me
It's been seven days since my uncle sent it back
Still not refunding the money?
I want to file a complaint.
The robot says
Hey, the return has been received.
Processing in progress
Let's actually think about this scenario
If you are a merchant on JD or Taobao
then you go to a store's customer service to complain
What is the customer service most likely to say
Dear, please don't be angry
I'll check it for you right away.
and then let me tell you
We have received the goods for this current order
Being processed
We will refund you the money immediately.
Please rest assured
Then the user experience will be much better
So, it's hoped that in the process of the robot's response
can also add some emotion recognition tools
When the user's question is clearly emotionally charged,
The robot should first provide comfort before giving an answer
Then for the algorithm requirement of emotion recognition
so we can clarify that
The input for this requirement is the user's question
The output is the user's emotional value
is neutral
positive or negative
Of course, there are some intelligent customer service robots on the market now
within negative emotions
further categorize whether the user is anxious or angry
In this example,
We will categorize all negative emotions as negative
this category
When the emotion recognition algorithm model is launched,
we expect the emotion recognition accuracy of a model
the accuracy rate can reach over 90%
Through technical research
we found
the industry implements emotion recognition
primarily uses classification algorithms
that is, for each user's question
are all categorized into an emotional classification
Let me briefly introduce to you
What is a classification algorithm
Classification algorithms can be divided into binary classification and multi-class classification.
AlphaNE is relatively simple
In the early stages of this model,
For example, we have studied a large number of this
photos of black sheep and white sheep
train such an algorithmic model
The function of this model is, hey, you give me a sheep
I'll tell you whether it's a white sheep or a black sheep
Then came a black sheep
Then the model also identifies it as a black sheep
then the model's judgment is correct
This is a binary classification scenario
The emotion recognition we aim to achieve requires
Categorize user questions into positive, negative, and neutral
This is a three-class classification problem
or called a multi-classification problem
In the context of this multi-classification problem,
When the model needs to learn some labeled data
For example, there are 20,000 such questions
These sentences need to be manually labeled.
positive negative neutral
These are divided into three categories.
Then the algorithm learns from
the data you annotated
After the learning process is completed
then trained such an algorithm model
The function of this model is that you give it a sentence
then my model will tell you the sentence after my judgment
whether it's positive, negative, or neutral
This is such an Emotions model
Here I want to mention
As an AI product manager
Why do you need to understand what kind of algorithm is being used?
or how exactly such a technology is implemented
Let's take the emotion recognition we just mentioned as an example
as an example
Sentence A: I'm going crazy, ah!
I want to complain
What about sentence B? Is it acceptable or not?
I'm in a hurry
Actually, sentence A is much worse than sentence B
From a human perception perspective
it is much more negative
because the user is about to file a complaint
He is already very angry
but the model's output shows that
Both sentences are classified as negative.
Because we're using a classification algorithm
The classification includes these three categories.
For sentence A and sentence B
then the model gives them similar scores
So you can't just because sentence A has a higher negative sentiment value
Sentence B has a relatively lower negative sentiment score.
you think the model should give a higher score to A
B is lower
As an AI product manager
in this regard
we need to understand this technology
should have a certain level of understanding
and be able to achieve some level of explainability
If in a real business scenario
Then, on the basis of identifying negative emotions,
You can add some keyword rules.
special handling for such scenarios
For example, if a complaint-related keyword is triggered
give it priority handling
For the requirement of emotion recognition,
We need to provide annotated data
social product manager
You should understand
accuracy of annotated data
is the upper limit of the effect that the algorithm model can achieve
For example, you have labeled 20,000 pieces of data
then among these 20,000 foreign language sentences
95% are correctly labeled
and 5% are incorrect
or ambiguous
then the maximum effect the model can achieve
is capable of achieving a recognition rate of 95%
Of course, it may still fall short
That is to say, the upper limit of the accuracy rate
can reach up to 95%
because it is learning from the manually annotated data you provided
an annotated dataset
and the final learned model
So when we're performing data annotation
usually we suggest that
The same batch of corpus will be annotated by at least 20,000 people.
Finally, we take the intersection
when the 20,000 annotators have discrepancies
we then conduct a verification and check
This demonstrates the importance of providing data annotation.
Here, let me tell you about the AI algorithms we work on.
The three pillars of AI are data, computing power, and algorithms.
Algorithm data accounts for 70%
A significant amount of work is also spent on collecting and preparing data.
For example, let's take such a classification model as an example
You have a fresh graduate newbie
with a senior algorithm engineer with years of experience to train
on the trained model
There is not much difference in terms of accuracy
at most, there can be a difference of two percent
So
If you want to achieve a good understanding of this AI algorithm model
Data is very important
As an AI product manager
In the process of tracking algorithm experimental results
First, you need to master
What are the common metrics for evaluating algorithm performance?
Taking the previously mentioned emotion recognition requirement as an example
We provided 20,000 standardized data samples
given to the algorithm engineers
We would recommend that 80% of it
for this data
20% of this is used for the training set
This data is used for the validation set
What does this mean
For example, among the 20,000 data points
There should be 16,000 pieces of data used for this algorithm.
to train a classification model
and four thousand pieces of data
This data is used to test the effectiveness of the model
conduct a test
At this point, we also need to introduce an inverse matrix
such a concept
based on the algorithmic model
to predict a positive emotional outcome
obtain these four basic metrics
We need to put it into the confusion matrix.
in this table
For example, in this test set,
True refers to sentences with positive emotions.
the model also considers it to be positive
we denote it as TP
placed in the top-left corner of the table
then in this test set
In this test set, the ground truth is positive sentiment
but the model identifies it as negative or neutral
this amount of data
I will record it as FA and place it in the lower-left corner of a table.
In this test set
Its true value should be negative or neutral
but the model predicts it as positive
We categorize such sentences as FP.
placed in the upper right corner of the table
In this test set
The true value should be negative or neutral
The model considers the sentence to be negative or neutral
such sentences
We record it as TA and place it in the bottom-right corner of the table.
Then, these four metrics
Let's present them together in this table
we obtain such a confusion matrix
Then through this confusion matrix
Actually, you can also see that
the TP in the upper left corner and the ta in the lower corner
is the number of correct predictions made by the model
Let's take a look at the positive, negative, and neutral categories
these three categories
How does the model's confusion matrix perform?
The predicted value is positive
if the true label is also positive
There are 1,435 instances where the predicted value is negative
true negative
5,643 items
predicted as positive
True false positives
There are 3,247 entries
OK, let's see through the final calculation
the statistical data
Let's take a look
So, how is the performance of our model?
In this context, we commonly use three key metrics
accuracy
recall rate and F1 score
So what does accuracy equal to?
how many of the samples that the algorithm considers correct are actually correct
the proportion it occupies
Let's calculate them separately, okay
For example, among the positive ones,
it can predict as positive
it is inherently positive
There are 1,435 entries.
So how is this calculated in this context?
this is 1435
plus 9052
divided by the sum of these four, right?
Add these two values together and divide by
This whole thing is the same as well
5643 plus 4708
divided by the sum of these four numbers
OK, the resulting accuracy is about 98%.
Similarly, based on this data, we can also derive the recall rate
and other F1 scores
The higher the accuracy,
the recall rate is also relatively high
We believe that this model is quite good.
The higher, the better
When we understand the actual computational performance of the algorithm
Then, before going live,
multi-dimensional data validation is also required
That is to say, based on your current business scenario
You need to reserve some test corpora for different scenarios
input this model for verification
Check the test results of the test corpus in different scenarios
Does its value meet the expectations in all cases?
Again, let's take the emotional recognition requirement as an example.
We trained a multi-category emotion recognition model
Next, we will extract a portion of the pre-sales questions
or extract a batch from after-sales issues
feed all the user questions into this model
have the model provide us with a result
For example, I sent 100 questions from the pre-sales stage
100 issues were extracted from the after-sales data
After being annotated post-tax
it is found that the model's accuracy for me
can basically achieve over 98%
then the model is good to go
If it's pre-sales or after-sales
in different business scenarios
or users from different channels
they have some different ways of phrasing it
different expressions
then the results provided by the Emotions recognition model
does not meet our expectations
then this model is unusable
then we need to feed more corpus into the Emotions recognition model
retrain it
Or we can base it on different business scenarios
or train for different industries.
If we target different scenarios
or training for different industries
a large number of models need to be trained here
it's not just one model
can solve all such scenarios
As an AI product manager
after your algorithm feature is launched
You need to continuously follow up on optimization and iteration
Optimization iteration mainly focuses on the following two aspects.
The first aspect is to collect online bad cases
Still taking the emotion recognition requirement as an example
You need to continuously follow up on
What are the issues reported by online users
it is clearly negative but was recognized as positive
or cases where there was clearly no emotion but were identified as emotional
annotate the data of these issues
and then provide it to the algorithm engineer for reference
have them update their model
and test the upper limit
The second aspect
Because our business is continuously evolving
So periodically
you'd better collect some updated online
annotate some user query corpus
provide to the algorithm engineers
update its model here
Let's summarize Bai Xiaojie.
As an AI product manager,
You should understand the capabilities of the algorithmic technology.
It then introduced what algorithms the intelligent customer service robot should have
and it particularly emphasized
then based on the algorithm's performance such a process
Of course, the steps in this process
will vary depending on different organizational structures and business scenarios
may vary
The three recommended steps to validate
First, propose algorithm requirements
You need to ensure that your requirements are granular enough
and be able to clarify
What is the input and output scope of the algorithm model?
What business metrics does this algorithm need to meet?
What are your expected business metrics?
The second step is to track the effectiveness of algorithm requirements.
You need to understand how the algorithmic formula is implemented
and provide annotated data to the algorithm during the follow-up of experimental results
at this stage
we introduced the confusion matrix
accuracy
recall and F1 score
these common metrics for evaluating algorithm performance
Finally, perform a multi-dimensional data validation.
After the third step is launched
continuously optimize the performance
collect some real user speech data
based on the adjustments and changes in business scenarios
promptly optimize and iterate your own model